Boston Parks Department. Records of the Boston Parks Department, (1890-1995)
Records,
(1890-1995)
Arnold Arboretum Archives of Harvard University, Jamaica Plain, MA 02130.
I A-6
Boston Parks Department
4 linear in, 1 box
Access to Finding Aid record in Hollis Classic or Hollis.
Current version of this finding aid is available at the Archives of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University.
In 1872 it was proposed that the Arboretum be combined with the Boston Parks System, with the hope that the lands would be protected from encroachment, taxation and seizure by eminent domain. These records were created as a result of the Arboretum's involvement in that process. The HOLLIS # for this collection is 008911492 and the file name is ajp00034.
Researchers seeking to examine archival materials are strongly encouraged to make an appointment. The Director, or an office of origin, may place restrictions on the use of some or all of its records. The extent and length of the restriction will be determined by the Director, office of origin, and the Archivist and will be enforced equally for all researchers.
The Arnold Arboretum was founded in 1872 according to the will of James Arnold on land willed to the Harvard College by Benjamin Bussey. Very soon after, the director Charles S. Sargent engaged Frederick Law Olmsted to begin planning the design of the grounds. At the same time it was proposed that the Arboretum be combined with the Boston Parks System, with the hope that the lands would be protected from encroachment, taxation and seizure by eminent domain. The plan was approved by the Boston City Council in December 1881 and ratified by the Boston parks commissioners and the president of Harvard College in 1882. The plan called for the College to sign the title of the land over to the City of Boston and the City to lease the land back to Harvard for $1 per year for 1000 years with the lease renewable at that time. The City retained lease to the land that was to be made into the Arboretum driveways. They also agreed to spend $75,000 to construct those driveways. They were to provide policing and promised not to tax the lands or allow any encroachments on the property. Harvard agreed to maintain the Arnold and Bussey trusts, maintain the living collections and open the grounds to the public at reasonable times.
The bulk of the materials consist of administrative papers relating to the interaction between the Arnold Arboretum and the Boston Parks Department, including general correspondence, and correspondence relating to the acquisition of the South Street tract and the installation of donations canisters. In addition there are several folders of copies of historical papers, including a copy of the indenture of 1882 between the City and Harvard College
- I: Correspondence
  Correspondence mainly between the Directors of the Arnold Arboretum, Karl Sax, and Richard A. Howard, and the Commissioners of the Boston Park Department, who where John J. Murphy until 1949, Frank R. Kelley until 1957, Martin F. Walsh until 1963, William J. Devine until 1967, John J. Tierney until 1970, Joseph E. Curtis until 1974, Anthony Forgione until 1975, Peter Meade until 1977.
  - 1948-1950., Folder 1:
    - Correspondence between Karl Sax and John J. Murphy, then Frank R. Kelley.
      Content includes building a road, specifically to the top of Peter's Hill, snow removal at the Arnold Arboretum, repairing macadam paths at the Arnold Arboretum, signage, dealing with drought, and repairing walls.
  - 1951-1955., Folder 2:
    - Correspondence between Karl Sax and Frank R. Kelley.
      Content includes fences in and around the Arnold Arboretum, signage, a road to the top of Peters Hill, parking permits, the removal of some Dutch Elm Disease infected Elms, the building of a garage on Walter St., keeping arboretum gates locked and in good condition, and other general maintenance needs.
    - Correspondents include Casey, Kelley, O'Keefe, Pigeon, Sax, Schwarten.
      1 letter from Thomas F. Casey of the Boston Police Department to Sax concerning the policing of the Arnold Arboretum after dark, 1 letter from Kelley to Rose Dopoyan of Milton High School and 1 letter from Kelley to E. F. Pigeon of Medford High School, both granting permission to park a bus in the arboretum parking lot, and 1 letter from Arthur J. O'Keefe to Lazella Schwarten of the Herbarium and Library in Cambridge concerning the naming of Peters Hill.
  - 1957-1965., Folder 3:
    - Correspondence between Howard and Kelley, then Walsh, then Devine.
      Content includes repairing benches, persecuting plant thieves, times that the gates are locked, driving permits, illegal dumping in the Arnold Arboretum, a memorial to Grace S. Batchelder, the Arnold Arboretum becoming a National Historic Site, and vandalism within the grounds. 1 letter from Kelley to captain John F. McElhinney of the Boston Police Department concerning police protection of the Arnold Arboretum, 1 letter to Howard from Joseph F. McLaughlin, Editor of "Tell it to Joe" concerning a complaint about cars in the Arnold Arboretum and 1 response to him from Howard, 2 letters from devine to Truman W. Eustis III regarding money left for the Arnold Arboretum in the will of Grace S. Batchelder, 1 letter from Howard to Edwin W. Small concerning the Arnold Arboretum becoming a National Historic Site.
  - 1966-1970., Folder 4:
    - Correspondence between Howard and Devine, then Howard and Tierney in 1967, then Curtis in 1970.
      Contents include vandalism by the "Shot Brothers," putting in a fence to keep out trash, lewd conduct of drivers within the Arnold Arboretum, a gift of spruce trees given by Peter L. Hornbeck, repairing or replacing the Arborway entrance, Arboretum Visiting Committee meeting, disposing of debris, parking permits, general maintenance of paths, roads, fences, gates, signs and water sources, protection of visitors and their property, 1 letter from Devine to Captain Cornelius F. O'Brien concerning vandalism at the Arnold Arboretum, 1 letter from Mayor of Boston John F. Collins to Howard and 1 response letter from Howard regarding the development of an Anti-Poverty Program, 1 letter from Peter L. Hornbeck, Assistant Professor of Landscape Architecture to Tierney, 1 letter from John J. Tierney to F. B. Jackson concerning a new service building.
  - 1971-1977., Folder 5:
    - Correspondence Between Howard and Curtis until 1974, then Forgione until 1975, then Meade.
      Contents include discussions of a bicycle path, general maintenance as well as repairs of damages as a result of heavy snow, and a plan to repair the driveways and paths of the Arnold Arboretum.
    - Correspondents include Cosgrove, Howard, Leahy, Moulton.
      1 letter from Marti F. Cosgrove, chief engineer, to Howard concerning a guard rail along the street, 1 letter from Howard to Mr. Donald C. Moulton concerning building a pedestrian walkway, 1 letter from Howard to Dean Richard Leahy concerning repairs to driveways, paths, fences, and gates.
  - 1978-1983., Folder 6:
    - Correspondents include Ashton, Berenson, Howard, Marks, Shaw, Stone.
      Correspondence between Howard and Robert G. Stone, then Peter S. Ashton and O. M. Shaw,; Paul F. Perkins,; Wendy Marks, and Paul S. Berenson.
- Photocopies of the sections pertaining to the Arnold Arboretum
  - Boston Parks Department annual reports, 1880-1889, Folder 1:
  - Boston Parks Department annual reports, 1890-1900, Folder 2:
- III: Administrative Papers
  - Maintenance
    photocopies
    - Expenditures for maintenance, 1943-1976, Folder 1:
      digest and photocopies of original City documents
    - Contract and specifications for grading for the Arnold Arboretum, 1890, Folder 2:
  - South Street Tract
    - Acquisition of the South Street Tract, 1992-1995, correspondence, maps and proposals, Folder 1:
  - Admissions
    - Voluntary admissions canisters, 1979-1983, correspondence, design specifications, Folder 1:
  - General Reports Records
    - Report of the Common Council on the Arnold Arboretum, 1881, photocopy, Folder 1:
    - Petition of the Taxpayers of Boston for the Arnold Arboretum, 1881, Folder 2:
    - Indenture between the City of Boston and Harvard College, 1882, copy, Folder 3:
    - Landscape restoration of the Olmsted Parks, 1995, Folder 4:
    - Rules and guides, n.d., Folder 5:
    - General papers, 1892-1990, Folder 6: